Guide to the William Thompson Sedgwick Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Thompson Sedgwick Papers
1864-1922
MS 1312
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, research material, writings and biographical material collected by C.-E.A. Winslow for a biography of Sedgwick, published in 1924. The correspondence (1879-1921) is with students and colleagues on professional matters, and the fragmentary research material concerns bacteriological studies of milk. For additional Sedgwick correspondence, see the C.-E.A. Winslow papers, MS749. The writings include articles, lecture notes, reports and essays. Also in the papers is a lengthy tribute to Sedgwick by George C. Whipple. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Sedgwick, W. T. (William Thompson), 1855-1921
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired as part of the C.-E.A. Winslow Papers (MS 749).
Associated Materials
Related material: C.-E.A. Winslow Papers (MS 749), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Research Materials. III. Writings. IV. Bibliographic Material.
Biographical / Historical
William Thompson Sedgwick (1855-1921), educator and bacteriologist, was one of the founders of the American public health profession. Educated at Yale (Ph.B., Sheffield Scientific School, 1877) and Johns Hopkins (Ph.D., 1881), Sedgwick taught at Johns Hopkins, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Harvard. He was responsible for founding schools of public health in both M.I.T. and Harvard.
The Sedgwick Papers at Yale were collected by C.-E.A. Winslow while he was preparing a biography of Sedgwick, A Pioneer of Public Health--William Thompson Sedgwick (1924) with E.O. Jordan and G.C. Whipple. The papers are made up of one and one-half linear feet of material that is arranged in four series: CORRESPONDENCE, RESEARCH MATERIAL, WRITINGS, and BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL. Although the manuscript group is fragmentary and incomplete, it represents the largest extant collection of Sedgwick's papers.
CORRESPONDENCE spans the years 1878 to 1920 and consists of correspondence from students and colleagues. The 1906 correspondence from students on the occasion of Sedgwick's thirtieth anniversary in teaching is of special interest. RESEARCH MATERIAL is largely undated and fragmentary and concerns bacteriological studies of milk. WRITINGS extends from 1879 to 1920 and includes articles, lecture notes and texts, reports, essays and occasional programs. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL includes a lengthy tribute to Sedgwick by George C. Whipple.
The Sedgwick Papers are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, and they were originally accessioned as part of the papers of C.-E.A. Winslow. For additional Sedgwick correspondence see the Winslow Papers (MS 749).
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, research material, writings and biographical material collected by C.-E.A. Winslow for a biography of Sedgwick, published in 1924. The correspondence (1879-1921) is with students and colleagues on professional matters, and the fragmentary research material concerns bacteriological studies of milk. For additional Sedgwick correspondence, see the C.-E.A. Winslow papers, MS749. The writings include articles, lecture notes, reports and essays. Also in the papers is a lengthy tribute to Sedgwick by George C. Whipple. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Milk -- Microbiology; Public health; Bacteriologists; Biologists; Educators; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Sedgwick, W. T. (William Thompson), 1855-1921; Whipple, George Chandler, 1866-1924; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957
- Correspondence, 1878-1921; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1878-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Research Material, 1879-1916; Series II; 1/4' (1/2 box)
  RESEARCH MATERIAL is arranged chronologically.
  - Research material, 1879, 1894, 1902-1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research material, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Research material, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research material, 1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1879-1920, undated; Series III; 1/2'(1 box)
  WRITINGS is arranged chronologically and contains four folders of undated material.
  - Writings: bibliography, 1879-1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings, 1879, 1885-1889 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Writings, 1892-1899 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Writings, 1900-1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1916-1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Biographical Material, 1864-1922; Series IV; 1/4'(1/2 box)
  BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, account book and notes, 1864, circa 1871, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Educational records, 1872-1877 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings, 1898-1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Copper plate, Circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and citations, 1904-1909, 1917-1922 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tributes, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 7)